<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jim McGaw&#39;s Blog</title>
    <description>Hiya. I&#39;m an open-source web engineer who likes to write.
</description>
    <link>http://yourdomain.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://yourdomain.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2016 11:57:26 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2016 11:57:26 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Disconnected</title>
        <description>A few years ago, before I disabled my Facebook account entirely, I turned off all notification emails, uninstalled the Facebook app, and taught myself not to automatically type in &quot;facebook.com&quot; in my browser&#39;s address bar whenever I got bored with the work I was doing on the computer. The latter one was the most challenging, since this was a habit that had been ingrained for several years.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I heard someone once joked that &quot;I don&#39;t even have a Facebook account!&quot; is the new &quot;I don&#39;t even own a TV!&quot; It&#39;s the mark of the self-righteous person who has chosen to liberate themselves from the technology of the lowest common denominator, and who has to derive their sense of self-worth from telling everyone else around them about how &lt;i&gt;grand&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;it is that they&#39;ve liberated themselves from it, while insinuating that all other people should follow their example.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;m not one to lecture; I&#39;m merely one to share my own story. I learned that Facebook, like television, is something that is best consumed with portion control. Instead of eating the ice cream right out of the carton, for example, you spoon out the amount you want into a bowl and eat out of the bowl. I&#39;m not a dietician, but knowing my own eating habits tells me that this tactic makes it far less likely that I&#39;m going to glance down 15 minutes later, and find myself staring at an empty carton and sticky spoon, realizing that I&#39;ve somehow&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;eaten the whole carton.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As they say: moderation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So I stopped going to the television to kill an indeterminate amount of time. Instead of looking for a new television series that would entertain me until I fell asleep, I started setting aside blocks of time in which I would watch something to mentally unwind, then step away to do something else. Of course, this works so long as the television series isn&#39;t one with dangling cliffhangers at the end of each episode that hook into your brain and pull you along into the next one.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Remember when Netflix didn&#39;t have the &quot;auto-play the next episode&quot; for TV shows? Remember when people used to complain about this? I remember complaining about it. Now that each TV show I put on is a slippery slope of wasted time, I have to wonder: was this really ever a &lt;i&gt;problem&lt;/i&gt;?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Anyhoo. Where was I? Ah, so a few years ago, I disconnected my email inbox from all social networking messaging. I removed the notifications from the mobile apps I left installed. Nothing from the platform would pull me into social media, save for my own impulses. For this reason, social media was trickier to disconnect from. This was partly because I got into Facebook when I had just moved across the country to a city where I didn&#39;t know a single soul except for my girlfriend, and I didn&#39;t have the requisite social skills to walk outside and &lt;i&gt;talk to strangers&lt;/i&gt;. Any ersatz social connection was better than none. I eventually made friends offline, but this didn&#39;t ease the difficulty of recusing myself from the social media...old habits and all that.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I even found that my habit of working with my email inbox constantly open in a browser tab was distracting. I now leave this closed most of the time. When I have it open, most of the emails I&#39;m getting from vendors sending me marketing junk skip my inbox and go to filters I&#39;ve set up. If my inbox alerts me to a new email, it&#39;s most likely a human and not a robot.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;ve been living this way, mostly disconnected from the immediate demands of technology, for the last couple of years. It has been liberating, but I believe it has also been responsible for some bouts of loneliness that I felt while I was adjusting. It&#39;s not a really a huge surprise, but after years of engaging in social media, there were withdrawal symptoms. I had to face the wrath of #FOMO, and to borrow from Homer Simpson, there was no place where people could hear my various witty remarks. (Their loss, of course.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Taking this step probably isn&#39;t for everyone. There have been long-term drawbacks. I don&#39;t keep my phone on me at all times, and even when I do, I&#39;ll often ignore it when I&#39;m with other people, so I&#39;ll be unresponsive to text messages from my friends to what might be considered, by modern standards, a fault. Even offline, conversations tend to crop up in my social circles about things that happened online, so sometimes I&#39;m that one person that needs to be shown the video that everyone else already saw on Facebook so I have context for the rest of some conversation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But overall, comparing the two, I&#39;d say that living without social media having its claws in my mind is much more enjoyable. I&#39;d suggest that anyone who&#39;s wired in all the time take the 30 minutes or so right now, and set up disconnection from social media or technology, as much as your vocation might comfortably permit.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don&#39;t put this off...try it right now. Try it for a day or, better yet, a week. If you can&#39;t bear the pain of #fomo, rest assured that social media will happily welcome you back with open arms. It&#39;s the place where everybody knows your name.
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/23/disconnected.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/23/disconnected.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Impact</title>
        <description>If there were one single thing I wish I could accomplish with my writing, it would be to make the reader more conscious and considerate of the emotional impact they&#39;re having on the people around them.
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/19/impact.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/19/impact.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Bottom of the Pyramid</title>
        <description>We like to tell ourselves stories. As we make sense of our lives, we cast ourselves as the protagonist in an ongoing narrative, surrounded by supporting characters.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The structure of fiction almost certainly proceeds from our tendency to do this. Even in large stories with several characters that are all given equal weight in the storyline, there always needs to be a central character for the audience to latch onto, who is elevated above all the others. We need this, because we are most comfortable with stories that match the one we&#39;re constantly telling ourselves: that there is one central character around whom everything revolves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The problem with this story structure is that real life is almost never like this. We spend our lives trying to write our own story, imagining that we&#39;re the the lead, even in situations in which we do not lead. Anything worth accomplishing in this world is never the effort of a single person, but of a group of people acting in concert. People don&#39;t coalesce around a single goal well when everyone thinks they are, or should be, in the lead role.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Our stories are real. Since they often define us, they are extremely important to our sense of self. The world in which I imagine living, the one in which I&#39;d like to live, is one where more people are willing to cast themselves in supporting roles.
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/17/the-bottom-of-the-pyramid.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/17/the-bottom-of-the-pyramid.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Can Men Be Feminists?</title>
        <description>Oddly, I see this question come up quite frequently. My initial gut reaction is: who cares? I would say that if a man wants to be supportive of a particular cause, why suggest that he cannot? I&#39;m not stricken with cancer, nor has any member of my family ever been, but I don&#39;t think the American Cancer Society would turn down my offer of support in helping fight the issue because of this reason. Perhaps feminism is distinct in a way that I&#39;m failing to identify.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Naturally, there is the risk that a man calling himself a feminist might do so for the wrong reasons, or he might misrepresent the movement itself. Many men tend to be sexist inadvertently, in ways of which they are not aware. A squadron of men running around with shirts reading &quot;This is what a feminist looks like&quot; while perpetuating rape culture could do more harm than good in their community. Making a movement completely inclusive allows it to spread to more people, but the median amount of passion and understanding of the core mission will most likely decrease.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Perhaps most importantly, if you use the measure of how much a person &quot;gets it&quot; in order to determine how worthy they are of being a card-carrying feminist, there are certainly women who call themselves feminists who would fail the litmus test as well. (Whatever such a test might entail.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&#39;s not a terrible question to ask if there should be a standard to which all feminists should hold themselves. Like any cause for social justice, I&#39;d believe this is something you should commit to over time, not only in word, but in deed. It shouldn&#39;t be enough to apply the label to yourself one day, then simply coast on whatever knowledge brought you to apply the label. Culture changes, as does the body of knowledge with which one must be familiar to understand the mechanics of oppression.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is especially true, I believe, if you are a man. Women live the understanding of their oppression in our society every day...though they may not be automatically or intuitively aware of how they should modify their actions in order to effect social change. As men we must continually seek this understanding, make an ongoing effort to scrutinize our own actions, and change them to not only avoid doing harm, but in an effort to do good.
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/16/can-men-be-feminists.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/16/can-men-be-feminists.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Acceptance Versus Encouragement</title>
        <description>Here&#39;s a tricky question I&#39;ve been struggling with as of late: when you&#39;re deal with another person, what is the correct balance between saying, &quot;As a human being, you are already good enough&quot; and saying, &quot;You have the potential to become much more than you already are&quot;? There&#39;s a pernicious insinuation in the latter that, while it may be encouraging, can also be seen as insulting, if it&#39;s offered in the wrong situation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When in doubt, I favor acceptance over encouragement. In my experience, people are naturally inclined to grow, to become more than they are, without encouragement. But most people struggle to accept themselves as they are, and you have to start from a place of acceptance before you understand how you can grow.
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/16/acceptance-versus-encouragement.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/16/acceptance-versus-encouragement.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Refractory Index</title>
        <description>People often ask me what I chose to start studying religious scripture. There&#39;s an old, possibly apocryphal tale about someone walking into W.C. Fields&#39; dressing room and catching him reading a Bible. In an effort to cover it up, he quickly said, &quot;I&#39;m looking for loopholes.&quot; In casual conversation, this is usually the answer I offer.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We understand a great deal about the structure of matter due to the field of crystallography. A certain part of the electromagnetic spectrum is sent as a beam into a solid and, based on its diffraction pattern or angle of the refracted rays, you can make a determination about the internal structure of the atoms of that solid. This requires that you first understand the properties of the beam of electromagnetic particles you sent into the solid.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I started studying the scriptures of the major religions, therefore, because I wanted to understand people better. The ideas that come from any given religion is the beam of electromagnetic particles that goes into us. No one has ever explained to me what their religion &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt;; they have merely explained to me what their religion &lt;i&gt;means to them&lt;/i&gt;.
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/15/refractory-index.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/15/refractory-index.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Across the Brownian Bridge</title>
        <description>I don&#39;t know what the future looks like. Perhaps that&#39;s better than either despair or hope.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In my early twenties, I had a tendency to assume the worst of people. I concluded that people were simply selfish little creatures who were entirely out for themselves. I wanted to believe this, so very much, because it gave me license to be selfish myself. If you can write it off as human nature, then you can assume it as your own nature.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Are human beings selfish by their very nature? I don&#39;t know. I think the tendencies are there, but I don&#39;t think they define who we are. They are merely one thing we can choose. We&#39;re not selfish beings, but we &lt;i&gt;try so hard&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;to be. And too often we succeed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;ve realized over the course of the last year or two that the selfish façade I&#39;ve constructed is a shell. It&#39;s a well-fed exterior that&#39;s hiding a malnourished interior that longs to care about something other than myself.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Assuming the worst from others has gotten me into plenty of trouble in the course of my life so far. I recognize this, so I&#39;ve taken the pains to excavate the innocent piece of me that remains buried beneath the rubble of my selfish exterior. In the hopes of accomplishing a different outcomes, I&#39;ve let this childish bit of me take the reigns. Unfortunately, this creature has led me down many terrible paths as well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Assuming the best of others doesn&#39;t work so well either, simply because, in an imperfect world, people are incapable of operating at their best at all times. If you expect the best from everyone all the time, then people start to feel pressure from you to be at their best, which is simply an impossible expectation to live up to. And if you wear your innocence on your sleeve, then people will quickly figure out how to take advantage of you. It dawns on your that perhaps the shell was there for good reasons.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I don&#39;t know what the future looks like. You can treat it as you would a person you meet, and assume it&#39;s going to be wonderful or terrible. But as with any person, the truth about the future, when it gets here, is probably going to lurk somewhere in between. You roll with the wonderful and the terrible parts as they come, knowing that all of them will pass, and that the composite whole is worth far more than the mere sum.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;ve always imagined myself walking into the future alone, like a lone cowboy strolling towards a setting sun across a barren desert, trying to avoid stepping on snakes or bumping into cacti. This is an imaginary myth that has no bearing in reality. The future is obscured from me, and what stands in the way is a massive throng of people.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Making your way into the future is like moving slowly through a crowded gymnasium at a networking event. Everywhere there are people bumping into one another, making their impressions on one another, then deflecting off to meet someone else. You move slowly, in Brownian fashion, erratically making your way to your destination as people come into and leave your life. Each person leaves an impression on you and alters your trajectory as you bounce away into another person. If you meet the right person you grab hands with them and twirl wildly in a circle with them until you get dizzy, fall down, and get up to do the whole thing again.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I don&#39;t know what the future looks like, just as I don&#39;t know who all of these people will be. I believe I&#39;m happier not knowing.
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/13/across-the-brownian-bridge.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/13/across-the-brownian-bridge.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Seek Power</title>
        <description>I&#39;m a white middle-class American male. I&#39;m far from a one-percenter, but needless to say, based on my demographics, I&#39;ve spent most of my life in privilege.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As men, society teaches us to seek power. We should go after the good job that gives us command over other people. We should go after a larger and larger salary as time marches on. We should find a woman and bring her under our wing in order to start a family. Etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is the lesson we&#39;re taught almost from the very first. What&#39;s usually not taught is what we should do with this power once we attain it. (Either that, or we&#39;ve obdurately ignored the lessons we were taught about our responsibility to others.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;More importantly, here&#39;s what we did not learn: power does not come automatically with privilege. Some measure of it does, and this certainly gives you more choices in your life compared to others who aren&#39;t as privileged as we are. But I&#39;ve found that the privileged men I&#39;ve known in my life went out into the world with high expectations about what their privilege entitled them to. They were all supposed to have fast-track careers at big companies that landed them somewhere near the top. They were all supposed to start massively successful entrepreneurial ventures. They were all supposed to get the trophy wife and have kids that didn&#39;t have cognitive disabilities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Perhaps you identify with this. Perhaps when you grew up, became a man, and ventured out into the world, you discovered that things weren&#39;t as easy as you were taught. In the wake of the mortgage crisis of 2008, I think we&#39;ve collectively learned this lesson in spades. Getting a college education and purchasing a house didn&#39;t magically shield us from the economic horrors and massive foreclosures that pulled the rug out from under many of us. Power concentrates at the top, and we suddenly learned that we were nowhere near as close to the top as we might have thought.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As men, we should seek power. But it is not power over our external world that yields the greatest return. It is power &lt;i&gt;over ourselves&lt;/i&gt;. Where society would teach us that we should conquer others around us in order to achieve our highest ideal, we must ignore this and play a different game with different rules. Men seek to influence. To control. They want to feel they can affect change over the forces that govern them and the people in their lives.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is important for men to do this, but before we can master the world around us, we must master ourselves. We either rule over our lower selves, our base instincts and desires, or they rule over us. This is the most difficult, and most important, conquest that exists in the world. We are each of us our own worst enemy. Sun-Tzu&#39;s first rule of war is to know your enemy, but most of us are so poorly acquainted with ourselves that it&#39;s impossible to believe that we&#39;ve conquered ourselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is only after we have learned to handle power over ourselves that we are ready to handle power over the world around us.
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/12/seek-power.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/12/seek-power.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Crossing the Chasm</title>
        <description>There&#39;s an old bumper sticker you see that calls out the importance of considering individual responsibility in the right-to-bear-arms debate: &quot;Guns don&#39;t kill people. People kill people.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Religion and politics are two major topics of conversation that have a reputation for being divisive. In my experience, they are not. People are.
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/11/crossing-the-chasm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/11/crossing-the-chasm.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hearts and Minds</title>
        <description>In adopting a worldview, here is the correctly ordered chronology of events:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;We separate feelings that make us feel good from those that make us feel bad. We desire to chase those feelings that make us feel good and avoid the bad ones.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;We choose beliefs that integrate with our existing beliefs, which are designed to keep the good feelings going, or avoid causing us bad feelings.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;We find the evidence to back up the beliefs we want to have, in order to justify the those beliefs that make us feel good.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;We live in a culture that values rationality and a scientific mindset over living at the whims of your own emotions and desires. After we adopt a worldview, we doublethink. The pernicious lie that we tell ourselves is that the steps I listed above occur in reverse. We deceive ourselves into thinking that we first found the evidence, then a belief system proceeded from this evidence, and then our feelings came from this belief system.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This becomes a problem when people interact with one another. People present &quot;evidence&quot; to me all the time about their worldview, convinced that in the face of this evidence, I&#39;ll come to believe what they believe. They believe that another rational person like myself will inevitably converge on the same conclusion that they have. The evidence will be input into my brain, the crank will turn, and out will pop the same belief. If this doesn&#39;t happen, then I can merely be dismissed as irrational.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It&#39;s in this way that we each try to coerce each other into believing what we ourselves believe. This is also the cause of frustration when others argue with our viewpoints. It so simple, we think to ourselves. The evidence is clear, the data points outline an arrow pointing to a singular conclusion, so why can&#39;t the other person see this?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Intellectualizing defeats itself because it leads us to believe that we can actually intellectualize. As a human being, I&#39;m little more than the sum of my desires. My beliefs about the world are a persona that represents these desires expressed in language.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So it is all with people. We spend years of feeling, thinking, and aggregating ideas about the world in order to formulate who we are and what we believe. Somehow, we trick ourselves into thinking that in the short space of a brief conversation with another person, we can use language to not only adequately represent who are, but to convince the other person that they should be more like us.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/10/hearts-and-minds.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://yourdomain.com/2016/05/10/hearts-and-minds.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
